<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>Questions, part 1</title>
        <author>
        	<name>Mihai</name>
        	<surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
            <tag>Task_1</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <question>
            <body>
                1.1	What is the "X" in 
                XML and what is its 
                significance? 
                Select one response and write the letter
                here 
            </body>
            <selectedanswer>b</selectedanswer>
            <options>
                <option>Extended</option>
                <option>Extensible</option>
                <option>Extreme</option>
                <option>Extendable</option>
            </options>
            <after>
                The "X" is significant because:
            </after>
            <answer>
                XML was designed to be extensible, which allows it to be used for a
                variety of applications. Many such XML-based formats have been
                defined, such as XML-RPC, SVG, XHTML, RSS  this proves XMLs
                usefulness, and would not be possible if not for XML being
                extensible.
            </answer>
        </question>
    
        <question>
            <body>
                1.2	What is a markup language? Select one response and write the letter
                here 
            </body>
            <selectedanswer>c</selectedanswer>
            <options>
                <option>A system of symbols to support the transmission of Morse code.</option>
                <option>A system to display website standards to which a website conforms,</option>
                <option>A system of embedded codes to make an electronic document display on a web page as required</option>
                <option>A system to only prepare documents for publication</option>
            </options>
            <after>
                What is a mark-up language and how is it used?
            </after>
            <answer>
                A mark-up language is used to give a special meaning to portions of
                text - this is accomplished by marking up the text with special
                tags, which have a meaning that is determined by the particular
                format of the XML file. Each type of XML file can have it's own
                tags, which are meaningless to other applications, or can have a
                different meaning.
            </answer>
        </question>
    
        <question>
            <body>
                1.3	What does SGML stand for? Select one response and write the letter
                here
            </body>
            <selectedanswer>a</selectedanswer>
        
            <options>
                <option>Standard Generalized Markup Language</option>
                <option>Structured Generalized Markup Language</option>
                <option>School of Global Management and Learning</option>
                <option>Simplified Generic Machine Language</option>
            </options>
        
            <after>
                What is the significance of SGML ?
            </after>
        
            <answer>
                SGML is important because most of the technologies that make
                the internet possible are based on it - such as (X)HTML and
                XML. The reason these languages were derived from SGML is that,
                due to it's complexity, writing an SGML parser is very
                difficlut. Furthermore, the expressive power SGML provides is
                not needed in many of the envisioned applications of markup
                languages. Therefore, subsets of SGML were chosen for
                particular applications.  
            </answer>
        </question>
    
        <question>
            <body>
                1.4	What is the relationship between SGML and XML? Select one response and write the letter
                here 
            </body>
            <selectedanswer>c</selectedanswer>
            <options>
                <option>SGML is based on XML</option>
                <option>SGML and XML are the basis for HTML</option>
                <option>SGML is a slimmed-down, streamlined version of XML</option>
                <option>XML is a slimmed-down, streamlined version of SGML</option>
            </options>
        
            <after>
                Describe and explain the relationship between SGML and XML
            </after>
        
            <answer>
                XML is based on SGML, but only has a subset of it's features. The creators
                of XML acknowledged the value of SGML, but felt is too 'heavy' for many
                purposes. Therefore, XML was developed - a light markup language, that can
                be extended to accommodate numerous applications.
            </answer>
        </question>
    
    
        <question>
            <body>
                1.5	What is the relationship between SGML and HTML? Select one response and write the letter
                here 
            </body>
            <selectedanswer>a</selectedanswer>
            <options>
                <option>HTML is a mark-up language derived from SGML</option>
                <option>SGML is a mark-up language derived from HTML</option>
                <option>Both are derived from XML</option>
                <option>Both are derived from AJAX</option>
            </options>
        
            <after>
                Give further  explanation  of the relationship between SGML and XML
            </after>
        
            <answer>
                HTML was derived from SGML, but most HTML documents do not validate as SGML
                documents. Since it was introduced, HTML accumulated many features that
                would not be practical to exclude for backward-compatibility purposes,
                which prevented HTML from being an SGML application - until HTML 4.0 -
                which fully conforms to the SGML standard.
            </answer>
        
        </question>
    
        <question>
            <body>
                1.6	Which of the following statements are true? Select one response and write the letter
                here
            </body>
            <selectedanswer>c</selectedanswer>
            <options>
                <option>Special-purpose packages have been derived from HTML</option>
                <option>HTML is an application derived from XML</option>
                <option>Special-purpose markup languages have been derived from XML</option>
                <option>XML is used to create HTML</option>
            </options>
        
            <after>
                Give examples to explain your answer
            </after>
        
            <answer>
                XML, being inherently extensible, has indeed been used as a basis for
                numerous other types of documents.  One of the most obvious examples of
                special-purpose XML-derived markup languages is XHTML - which is a
                re-formulation of HTML 4 document types as applications of XML 1.0.  SVG,
                Scalable Vector Graphics, is a format used to represent images using vector
                graphics, which is also an application of XML. XML is also used,
                internally, for recent Microsoft document types such as docx.
            </answer>
        </question>
    </body>

</blog_post>
