<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>Questions, part 2</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>2 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <question>
            <body>
                1.7	Which of the following statements DOES NOT apply to XML?  Select one response and write the letter
                here
            </body>
            <selected_answer>b</selected_answer>
            <options>
                <option>XML is a set of rules for encoding documents electronically</option>
                <option>XML is a predecessor of SGML</option>
                <option>XML explicitly identifies the knowledge structure in the encoded document, so that software packages can use this structure</option>
                <option>XML approach allow you to specify the presentation of the document, and the hypertext links</option>
            </options>
            
            <after>
                Explain your choice 
            </after>
            
            <answer>
                SGML is not a predecessor of SGML, to the contrary, XML was derived from SGML,
                as SGML was unnecessarily complex for some tasks.
            </answer>
        </question>

        <question>
            <body>
                1.8 Which of the following statements DOES NOT apply to XML?  Select one response and write the letter
                here
            </body>
            <selected_answer>d</selected_answer>
            <options>
                <option>XML underpins the www</option>
                <option>XML underpins office apps</option>
                <option>XML supports the creation of new markup languages</option>
                <option>XML is written in Java</option>
            </options>
            
            <after>
                Give examples  to illustrate your answers               
            </after>
            
            <answer>
                It is incorrect to say that XML is written in a specific
                programming language; XML is a standard, defined by the W3C.
                XML files are text files, which are not written in any
                particular programming language, and the application which
                consumes a particular flavor of XML files can be written in any
                programming language.
            </answer>
        </question>

        <question>
            <body>
                1.9 What does XIML stand for? Select one response and write the letter
                here
            </body>
            <selected_answer>c</selected_answer>
            <options>
                <option>Extensible Intelligent Markup Language</option>
                <option>Extended Invisible Markup Language </option>
                <option>Extensible Interface Markup Language</option>
                <option>Extraterrestrial Interactive Markup Language</option>
            </options>
            
            <after>
                Explain the implications of this acronym                
            </after>
            
            <answer>
                XIML was created to address the lack of a standardized method
                of representing interaction data, the data that relates to user
                interfaces. It is a markup language based on XML, which is
                extensible ( hence the 'X', from 'eXtensible' ), 
            </answer>
        </question>

        <question>
            <body>
                1.10 What is the purpose of XIML? Select one response and write the letter
                here
            </body>
            <selected_answer>a</selected_answer>
            <options>
                <option>A Universal Language for User Interfaces</option>
                <option>A Markup Language Intelligent Applications</option>
                <option>A Language for Unseen Web Features</option>
                <option>A Markup Language for Extraterrestrial Maps</option>
            </options>
            
            <after>
                Why is XIML needed? 
            </after>
            
            <answer>
                While XML provides the needed framework for creating various
                document types, no such framework exists for interaction data.
                This is the problem XIML addresses - it provides developers
                with a way to represent and manipulate interaction data. One of
                the benefits is that a XIML user interface could have multiple
                target displays - for example, one for the web ( which would
                output HTML code), and another one for  the .NET framework on
                Windows - which would generate the corresponding C# code.
            </answer>
        </question>
        
    </body>

</blog_post>        
