<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>Scalable Vector Graphics</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>SVG</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>

        <p>
            Scalable Vector Graphics ( SVG ) relies on text for describing an image. It
            also supports the inclusion of raster data, however the mainstay of SVG is
            textual description of graphic data. For example, the following SVG document
            contains a red circle with a black outline:
        </p>

<code>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?&gt;
&lt;svg
   xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#"
   xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
   xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
   version="1.1"
   width="100"
   height="100"
   id="svg2"&gt;
  &lt;g
     transform="translate(0,-952.36218)"
     id="layer1"&gt;
    &lt;path
       d="m 90,50 a 40,40 0 1 1 -80,0 40,40 0 1 1 80,0 z"
       transform="translate(0,952.36218)"
       id="path2987"
       style="fill:#ff0000;
              fill-rule:evenodd;
              stroke:#000000;
              stroke-width:1px;
              stroke-linecap:butt;
              stroke-linejoin:miter;
              stroke-opacity:1" 
    /&gt;
  &lt;/g&gt;
&lt;/svg&gt;
</code>

        <p>
            As it is obvious from the document above, SVG is an application of XML - valid
            SVG documents are also validate as XML. It also showcases how graphical data is
            stored inside the SVG file - as XML elements, with graphical properties
            described via attributes. The circle is represented by the path element - the
            'd' element is actually short for 'Path Data', and describes it's shape. (
            http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/paths.html#PathData ). Other properties of the
            circle, such as it's fill colour and stroke width/colour are described via
            attributes, as visible in the above example.
        </p>

        <p>
            The SVG specification has multiple profiles; for example, the SVG Mobile
            Recommendation ( http://www.w3.org/TR/SVGMobile/ ) defines the SVG Tiny and SVG
            Basic mobile profiles. SVG Tiny is targeted at highly restricted mobile
            devices, while SVG Basic is meant to be suitable for higher level mobile
            devices.
        </p>

        <p>
            One of the major issues concerning SVG is a reduced browser adoption rate.
            Although the most recent versions of all major browsers have at least some
            level of support for SVG images, some older, but still widely-used versions do
            not support SVG; Internet Explorer fully supports the SVG Basic specification
            only since version 9, released on March 14th 2011.
        </p>
        
    </body>

</blog_post>        
