<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>What is the importance of the first line of an XML document? </title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            The first line of an XML document must not be blank, since the document will
            fail the well-formedness test, and cannot be a valid XML document. As described
            in the standard, an XML document should begin with an XML declaration which
            specifies the version of XML being used.
            (http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126/#sec-prolog-dtd )
        </p>
        <p>
            However, a document not declaring the XML version on the first line can still
            pass the well-formedness test, but it cannot be a valid document. If the first
            line is blank, it cannot be well-formed, nor valid.
        </p>
        <p>
            For example, the following is a well-formed XML document, but not valid:
        </p>
<code>
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;foo&gt;This is the content of the foo element&lt;/foo&gt; 
</code>
        <p>
            This can be tested in an XML validator; for example, the one found at
            http://www.validome.org/xml/validate/: As visible from above, the document is
            not valid because nowhere is the &lt;foo&gt; element declared. However, if we only
            test for well-formedness:
        </p>
        <p>
            So summarize, the first line of an XML file should be used to specify the
            version of XML used; but it can also be any element, as long as it is not
            blank. However, a document without the declaration of the version of XML used
            cannot be valid - it can be well-formed, assuming XML syntax is respected
            throughout the file.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
