<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>What is XML well-formedness and how could you measure it?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Nov 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
            <tag>well-formedness</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>

        <p>
            If an XML document is well-formed, it conforms to the syntax rules, as defined
            in the XML standard. Unlike HTML, the XML standard is very strict, and does not
            tolerate errors such as the omission of a closing tag, or having different
            cases in the opening and closing tags; for example, the following is not a
            well-formed XML document:
        </p>

<code>
1 &lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
2 &lt;person&gt;
3     &lt;name&gt;John Smith&lt;/Name&gt;
4 &lt;/person&gt;
</code>

        <p>
            Although the "name" tag was closed, the closing tag tag should have the same
            casing as the opening tag, therefore this document is not a well-formed XML
            file. The line should be: &lt;name&gt;John Smith&lt;/name&gt; to form a well-formed XML
            document.
        </p>

        <p>
            Well-formedness also implies <em>correct nesting</em>; for example, the following code
            is not well-formed because the &lt;surname&gt; tag was opened before the &lt;name&gt; tag
            was closed, therefore the two tags overlap - which is not allowed in XML.
        </p>

        <p>Wrong:</p>

<code>
&lt;name&gt;John&lt;surname&gt;Smith&lt;/name&gt;&lt;/surname&gt;
</code>

        <p>Correct:</p>
<code>
&lt;name&gt;John&lt;/name&gt;&lt;surname&gt;Smith&lt;/surname&gt; 
</code>

        <p>
            Another way in which documents can fail the well-formedness test is by not
            having a single root tag; in other words, all of the tags inside the document
            must reside inside a unique pair of opening and closing tags. But it doesn't
            have to be the xml tag; it could be any tag ( with a valid name, of course ).
        </p>

        <p>
            Well-formedness can be checked with special tools - for example, the w3scools
            validator (http://www.w3schools.com/xml/xml_validator.asp); but due to the
            strictness of the XML standard, the parser should abort at the first
            encountered error. Therefore, the number of errors is rarely important; what
            matters is whether the whole document is valid.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
