<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>What are the differences between elements and attributes and what are their different uses?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
            <tag>element</tag>
            <tag>attribute</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>

        <p>
            As defined in the XML standard, a well-formed XML document must contain one or
            more elements; an element is has the form STag content ETag - it consists of
            content, enclosed between a start tag and an end tag. An XML document will not
            be valid if the name of the start tag does not match, case-sensitively, the end
            tag.
        </p>
        <p>
            To ensure validity of the document, all contained elements must be valid - it
            must respect XML syntax, and the DTD or XML Schema, if it has one. If the
            element is defined empty, then it must not have any content, not even comments
            or whitespace. Elements are used for the semantic markup of the XML document.
        </p>
        <p>
            An element can have zero, one or more attributes, which are declared inside an
            attribute-list declaration and are used to describe various properties of the
            element they are attached to. Attribute-list declarations can also be used to
            provide default values for attributes. To ensure well-formedness, an attribute
            must not appear more than one time in the same tag. Another well-formedness
            constraint is that attribute values must not contain the '&lt;' character, and
            that values must be enclosed in quotes.
        </p>
        <p>
            The exact meaning of an attribute, and how to interpret it's value, depends on
            the particular XML implementation. For example, XHTML supports the "id"
            attribute - which is meant to have as a value a document-wide unique id, to be
            used for styling or layout. Other types of XML documents might also declare
            "id" attribute, but it might have a different meaning, and therefore no
            assumptions should be made.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
