<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>XML Security</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>10 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
            <tag>security</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            XML is becoming increasingly common, and therefore security issues are also
            having an increased importance. Given that XML is frequently used in e-commerce,
            businesses need ways to ensure that stored data is secure, and prevent unauthorized
            access. This is especially important due to the textual nature of XML - a simple
            text editor can be used to view the contents and extract sensitive data.
        </p>

        <p>
            A number of security-related technologies have emerged, one of the most important
            ones being XACML - the eXtensible Access Control Markup Language. XACML allows for
            controlling access to information via rules and policies. Other significant
            initiatives are XML signature and XML encryption.
        </p>

        <p>
            The concept of digital signatures is not new, and mature standards have been in
            place for quite some time. But existing technologies only allow signing individual
            files. Given the hierarchical nature of XML, more granularity is highly desirable -
            in other words, the ability to sign portions of an XML document. This is the role
            fulfilled by XML signature. The high-level algorithm is quite simple - the element
            to be signed is hashed, the hash being stored inside a <var>DigestValue</var> element.
            Another digest ( usually a hash ) is produced from this element and is cryptographically
            signed. The XML signature is then inserted in the <var>signature</var> element.
        </p>

        <p>
            XML encryption operates on similar principles to XML signatures - it allows the
            encryption of XML documents with a high granularity, enabling the encryption of
            portions of a document. An additional advantage is that different encryption keys
            and algorithms can be used for each encrypted portion, allowing precise control
            over who can use which portions of the document.
        </p>

        <p>
            XML encryption is especially important in a business environment. For example,
            a delivery company might define an XML document type which contains one element
            which contains information about the client, and billing information, and one
            element containing information about the contents of the delivered package. The
            driver will have the key for viewing the client information, while the client
            might be sent via email the key for him to be able to view information about the
            content and check if anything is missing.
        </p>
        
    </body>

</blog_post>        
