<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>16 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            This report aims to provide an overview of the XML landscape - what technologies
            are available, in what state of development and acceptance are they, and provide
            examples of how they are used.
        </p>

        <p>
            In the first part, a number of frequently asked questions about XML and related
            technologies are answerd, providing the reader with a high-level overview of many
            of the topics which will be covered in more detail later in the report. Basic
            concepts relating to XML are discussed in this topic, such as well-formedness,
            validation, namespaces, elements and attributes. Also included is a
            high-level discussion about the semantic web.
        </p>

        <p>
            The second part of the report discusses various technologies, some of which
            vital to XML, such as XPath and XLink. Other technologies are based on XML,
            such as XIML and XUL, while AJAX and the concept of the DOM are more loosly
            related to XML. The W3C XML Schema is also described, explaining how the need
            for such a technology emerged and how does W3C XML Schema fulfills its role.
        </p>

        <p>
            In the third part, the topics of styling and transforming XML documents is
            adressed. Technologies such as CSS and XSL are discussed, providing examples
            of how they can be used to style XML documents, and for generating XHTML
            documents.
        </p>

        <p>
            More specific topics are explored in Part Four - such as Scalable Vector
            Graphics, and how can XML be used to represent a logical data model. This
            part also includes a section discussing the .docx format used by recent
            versions of Microsoft Office, and how it relates to the older .doc format.
            Another section is dedicated to a review of one of the most popular
            XML IDEs, XML Spy, 
        </p>

        <p>
            The fifth, and final part of this report explores some of the downsides of
            XML, and some of the problems which could be encountered while authoring or
            using XML documents. A case study of a badly written XML document is analyzed,
            and also included in Part Five is a discussion of security in the context
            of XML documents, along with a section on how encodings are used in XML.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
