<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>What is AJAX and what are its purposes?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
            <tag>AJAX</tag>
            <tag>XMLHttpRequest</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            AJAX stands for Asynchronous JavaScript and XML, and is a group of technologies
            used to create dynamic web pages. The main objective of AJAX is to allow pages
            to have their content modified, without having to re-download the whole page
            again.
        </p>
        <p>
            Before AJAX become widespread, most websites relied mostly on separate HTML
            files for displaying even dynamic content - such as constantly changing game
            scores, displayed by a betting company's website. This has proven troublesome
            both for the company, because each time the information to be displayed
            changed, the server had to send a new, updated HTML file - which was costly due
            to heavy bandwidth usage. It was also inconvenient for the users, since the
            whole page had to be reloaded.
        </p>
        <p>
            Therefore, the need for methods such as AJAX became apparent. It was first
            implemented by Microsoft's Internet Explorer, taking the form of iframe
            elements - which allowed only for parts of a webpage to be updated by the
            server. This technology evolved into the XMLHttpRequest JavaScript object,
            which forms the backbone of current AJAX technologies and is supported by all
            modern browsers.
        </p>
        <p>
            However, implementation by most browsers did not translate into wide adoption,
            and such technologies remained uncommon until their successful employment by
            Microsoft and Google in large-scale applications such as Outlook Web Access and
            Gmail. This proved the value and usefulness of AJAX technologies, and spurred
            their adoption for mainstream web development.
        </p>
        <p>
            Taking a website which displays football scores of on-going games, without AJAX
            the users would have to re-download the whole HTML file in order to notice any
            changes in scores. But it would be much better to be able to re-download just
            the XML file containing the scores, and update the HTML file accordingly, and
            AJAX makes that possible. 
        </p>
        <p>
            An XMLHttpRequest object would be created from the JavaScript file, and a
            function would be called when the object's readyState property changes ( via
            the xhr.onreadystatechange property, assuming the XMLHttpRequest object is
            named xhr ) The function would parse the retrieved data, and update the HTML
            code currently loaded in the user's browser accordingly, without having to
            re-download all of the HTML code from the server.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
