<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>What is the current status of CSS?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>CSS</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            finalized standard is CSS2.1 - which became a W3C Recommendation on the 7th of
            July 2011. CSS2.1 was developed after numerous flaws were found in CSS2, and
            some features were not implemented by browsers. CSS2 is currently not
            maintained (http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-CSS2-20080411/), and W3C points
            authors and implementors to the CSS2.1 specification, effectively admitting
            that CSS2 is obsolete. CSS2.1 also includes some features initially scheduled
            for CSS3, but it is mainly a "snapshot" of CSS usage at the time it was
            published (http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/), encompassing features that were widely
            implemented by browsers at the time the recommendation was published.
        </p>
        <p>
            CSS2.1, therefore, was a temporary, transitional solution, to easy the pain of
            web developers at the time and provide guidance for browser implementors. Work
            on CSS3 has begun around the time the CSS2 recommendation was published. But,
            unlike CSS2, the CSS level 3 is not a monolithic specification; instead,
            requirements are classified into modules, and each module can have a different
            priority for W3C, and level of implementation by browsers.
        </p>
        <p>
            For example, Level 3 CSS Backgrounds and Borders is currently classified as
            having "High Priority", and is a Candidate Requirement - which means it was
            widely reviewed, and satisfies W3C's technical requirements
            (http://www.w3.org/2005/10/Process-20051014/tr#q73); if implementation
            experience is deemed satisfactory, it will gain a Proposed Recommendation
            status. Currently, there is no document describing the CSS3 standard, but
            separate documents are available for each module. For example, the document for
            Level 3 CSS Backgrounds and Borders can be found here:
            http://www.w3.org/TR/css3-background/.
        </p>
        <p>
            Browser can have different levels of support for different CSS Level 3 modules;
            browser implementors are encouraged to define compatibility with Level 3 on a
            per-module basis, instead of individual features, or CSS 3 as a whole. Browser
            implementors are more likely to concentrate on implementing modules, than
            individual features.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
