<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>What are the implications of the concept of the document tree?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            The concept of document tree is enforced in XML files. Most of the times, it
            can also be correctly extracted from HTML files, where it is usually accessed
            and manipulated via JavaScript using the Document Object Model (DOM) API. The
            term 'document tree' is usually used in the context of XML files, while the DOM
            is associated mostly with HTML files - although the two terms can, and are
            sometimes used interchangeably.
        </p>
        <p>
            In the context of XML files, the concept of the document tree is crucial to a
            number of aspects. First of all, every XML file contains ( or can be considered
            as being ) a document tree - with the root element as the root of the document
            tree, and each subsequent element forming a branch. The last element on a
            branch is called a 'leaf'.
        </p>
        <p>
            One of the implications concerns XML parsers and accessing API's - due to it's
            tree structure, XML documents are commonly parsed and stored into memory as a
            tree data structure, with each node representing an element. The DOM is the
            most common convention for representing and interacting with XML documents.
        </p>
        <p>
            The document tree is also relied on by XPath - which is used to address parts
            of an XML document. XPath uses a path notation ( hence the name ) similar to
            URL notations to navigate through the hierarchical structure of an XML document
            - the document tree. 
        </p>
        <p>
            XSL relies on XPath - and therefore, on the document tree - to select elements
            which to style and modify.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
