<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>How can an XML document be best presented?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            An XML document can be presented by styling it with CSS, but XSLT ( Extensible
            Stylesheet Language Transformation ) is preferred. XSLT is a language which
            itself is XML, and can be used for a number of transformations of XML
            documents.
        </p>
        <p>
            One common application of XSLT is for transforming an XML document into HTML,
            which will be presented to the user. The advantages of this approach are
            obvious; it allows a straightforward way of presenting content, as opposed to
            the more traditional way of storing data in a database, extracting it, and
            generating HTML from it. Using XSLT represents a simpler solution, and
            therefore less room for errors.
        </p>
        <p>
            XSLT can also be used to target various displays, or can be used in combination
            with XSL Formatting Objects to generate files in a variety of formats,
            including PDF documents and PNG images. One of the main advantages of using
            XSLT is that XSLT processors can be either client-side, or server-side.
        </p>
        <p>
            The presentation of XML documents, transformed using XSLT is not limited to
            websites; XSLT transformations are supported by Windows XP ( via MSXML3 ) and
            the GNOME desktop environment for Linux. XSLT fully leverages the advantages
            offered by being written in XML - it is a widely available and versatile
            technology, that can be adapted to various purposes, and parsers are relatively
            easy to write because of the numerous existing applications.
        </p>
    </body>

</blog_post>        
