<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<blog_post>
    <head>
        <title>What is the DOM ?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mihai</name>
            <surname>Rotaru</surname>
        </author>
        <date>1 Dec 2011</date>
        <tags>
            <tag>XML</tag>
            <tag>DOM</tag>
        </tags>
    </head>

    <body>
        <p>
            The DOM is an interface which provides a way of accessing and modifying
            structured documents, such as XML, XHTM and SVG. The DOM is usually accessed
            via it's public API, in a platform- and operating system-independent manner.
        </p>
        <p>
            The DOM has a troubled history, due to the fact that the early browsers market
            was very competitive, which reflected negatively on the willingness of the
            companies producing them to cooperate, develop and implement standards. W3C
            later managed to get companies such as Netscape and Microsoft to collaborate
            and develop a standard for a scripting language ( ECMAScript ), and a DOM
            afterwards, in late 1998.
        </p>
        <p>
            The concept of a DOM is used by browsers, which expose an API to enable
            JavaScript code to access and modify the DOM. For example, the following code
            will find an element which has the 'foo' id and make it's background colour
            green:
        </p>
<code>document.getElementById('foo').backgroundColor="green";</code>
        <p>
            This example illustrates a few important concepts about the DOM - instead of
            being a monolithic specification, it is divided into several separate
            documents, each describing a specific area. For Level 2 DOM, it comprises a
            'Core' ( http://www.w3.org/TR/2000/REC-DOM-Level-2-Core-20001113/ ), and the
            other recommendations extend on it. For example, the Level 2 HTML DOM extends
            some components which are part of the 'Core' specification, specializing them
            according to the needs of HTML. The HTML DOM 'HTMLDocument' interface, for
            example (
            http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/REC-DOM-Level-2-HTML-20030109/html.html#ID-26809268 )
            was derived from the core 'Document' interface, and similarly the HTMLElement
            interface was derived from the core 'Element' interface.
        </p>
        <p>
            Such extensions of the 'Core' DOM allow for a wider range of application, and
            therefore more uses. The aforementioned HTML DOM allows for HTM-specific
            manipulation - for example, hiding an element with a certain ID. The DOM Level
            2 Style specification allows scripts to dynamically access and update the
            content of stylesheets, therefore affecting how the document looks.
        </p>

    </body>

</blog_post>        
